Guide to the Temple Freda [Bryan, TX] collection MS 811
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Temple Freda [Bryan, TX] collection
1912-2006
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Aron, Sheila
MS 811
0.5 Linear Feet 1 Box
The Temple Freda collection is made up of documents, photographs, and news clippings concerning one of the oldest religious buildings in Bryan, Texas. Though used for different things over the years, Temple Freda remains stalwart in its support for the Jewish community in Bryan, interacting with both congregation Beth Shalom, and the A&M Hillel in College Station.
Biographical / Historical
Named after Ethel Freda Kaczer, Temple Freda is one of the three oldest religious buildings still in use in Bryan, Texas, where it was restored by a group of citizens in 2013. Temple Freda is on the National Register of Historic Places of Texas and is used today as a center for community activities such as weddings, small receptions, and educational activities.
Temple Freda maintains close connections with Jewish congregations in the area. When Texas A and M University Hillel opened up a building in College Station in 1958, many members of the then-temple began to attend services at the Hillel foundation building, which houses Temple Freda's Torah. Other congregants joined Congregation Beth Shalom when it was founded in 1968, and Temple Freda's cemetery is now under that congregation's care. The temple has also been a focus for Texas A and M University's Center of Heritage Conservation since 1982.
Scope and Contents
The Temple Freda collection contains official documents, news clippings and newsletters, photographs, correspondence, interview transcripts, and a brief written history of the temple itself. The materials are in good condition and range in date from 1912 to 2006. Despite its small size, researchers interested in the history of Jewish congregations in Texas, the architectural significance of synagogues, or the Jewish community in Bryan would find this collection enlightening.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Sheila Aron donated the papers in November of 2018.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in a single general series, sorted by date, with a single sub-series for Press.
Index Terms
Subjects
Newspapers -- Sections, columns, etc.; Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
photographs; newsletters; letters (correspondence); interviews; transcripts; legal documents
Subjects (Persons)
Aron, Sheila; Unknown
- Series I: Documents
  - Official Documents, 1912, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Press, 1913-2006
    - Press: Newspaper Clippings, 1913, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Press: Newsletters, 1994, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Press: Jewish Herald-Voice, 2006-04-13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, 1997-06 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1980, June 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interview Transcripts, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Founding of Temple Freda of Bryan, Texas," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)